yes I'm recording now because you me
will you be editing or you just use it
live yes just probably just use it as it
is because I don't have to edit alright
but what you were just saying I think
that that's really I I agree well let's
let's let's let's have a little start to
it yeah so why don't you just say hello
or something well thanks so much that we
were actually making time to both of us
making time to have a opportunity to
talk which is really nice on Easter
Sunday probably a very strange
Easter Sunday for most people who even
care to celebrate Easter or have any
relationship to Easter but it's it's a
lot of families who for the first time
don't get to be with each other and and
even those ones that maybe the lucky
ones they are the ones are worried about
people in hospital or people taking care
of people in hospital so yeah strange
strange days wonderful to see you again
John it's been a while just leave it
parked um thank you for asking me it's
great to be here and yeah we we just
before we started recording we have this
brief you were saying that in many ways
ecosystems restoration camp has also
been a strategy to prepare people for
the skills we need in crises to come and
at the same time do what is possible to
do to ameliorate the crisis that are
already on the horizon
um and now we're kind of right in the
middle of a crisis that will just
increased and the need for such work and
and I completely agree for me what I'm
interested in is is the way to scale
link what is effectively a relatively
small piece of land and a bunch of
people coming together to learn on that
peach piece of land how to restore it to
its wider community in its regional
context like the way that common land
works on landscape skate scales and then
the ERC in Spain was was just a small
part of that and I think that that
scaling in structure I find that she
really
interesting because that also bridges it
into how to provide for an entire small
city in its region and how do you see
the way that as more and more years he's
established themselves around the world
that they don't become like to the small
anarchic training grounds but a real mix
of people really wanting to also engage
with mainstream and help normal people
in learning how to restore ecosystems
yeah I think that's the real that's the
real goal so the the hardest part
usually is to start and what we what we
see now is that there are very large
numbers of organizations and very large
numbers of individuals around the world
who share the same intention
understanding that we need to have clean
drinking water we should be able to
drink from the rivers really and we need
to have fertile organic soils with
healthy microbiologic communities both
bacterial and fungal communities that
have a important and and vital role in
creating life on Earth and so to imagine
the earth without these healthy
microbiological communities is sort of
ridiculous really and then we need to
understand the role of the biomass the
height of the canopy the accumulation of
organic materials changing the the soil
temperatures the the the temperatures on
the surface of the earth and what would
that does to affect the hydrological
cycle the circulation of moisture the
natural regulation of the climate and
then probably most important we have to
understand
the relationships between all the
various species and the the primacy
really of biodiversity that this is
really the expression of evolutionary
succession and it's critical for health
and for balance in the earth so these
these particular things are natural laws
they're not something that's at my
opinion or anybody you know it doesn't
matter what we think about it matters
that we understand these these things
because these are giving us an idea
yeah they produce the air and the water
in the soil so the the camps idea is not
to just restore a tiny place the camps
idea is I think you need to separate it
into infrastructure and mission you know
so the the the infrastructure is a way
to allow people to do this work to get
the knowledge that they need and we can
also use this at a time like this where
we're in crisis I think in the last
three weeks over 16 million people in
the United States became unemployed and
that's in addition to the vast numbers
of homeless in and marginal people
already so that's probably going to
increase by tens of millions of people
over the next couple of months
I'm completely aligned with you like I
am and I think I think that most of the
people that would listen to us
completely understand that this is the
great work of our time and you have
letters and started a whole movement of
people wanting to do this work what I'm
saying is I've been on this mission as
well for the like 15 20 years and what I
having worked with many of the pioneer
villages that basically fully
established eco village restoration
comes with initiatives that have
actually restored large landscape areas
whether horrible or Tamera or fintan or
they are the the projects that have
grown out of fent on and and what I've
learned by being with these communities
is that there comes a point that these
projects also need to engage with the
people who mean well but are stuck in
public authorities of the local and
regional government the local mayor then
the the local guy of the planning office
and and somehow really embed this as a
whole regional economic activity in the
state well you know like yeah I mean
what we see I think you you have to you
know I take a slightly different tack
than you do because first of all I think
that the ecosystem restoration camps and
eco villages have are symbiotic but
they're not the same I think that the
ecosystem restoration camps are a
temporary step for a lot of people and
when those people move on that a next
group of people need to get the same
information and when they have the
ability to control water soil plants and
biodiversity and they have some
experience in interpersonal relations
and conflict resolution then they can go
to ecosystem restoration camps they'll
be much better at making these types of
long-term societal changes work without
those skills I think it will be very
very hard and on the other side about
economics I think that we have to look
at economics business as usual and
realize that we might not be able to do
business as usual in the future that we
may be looking at the collapse of
financial systems and the collapse of
currencies here so in that case we
really need to figure out and live that
change we want to see on the earth so
this we need to work with everybody then
otherwise yes it has to be a collective
consciousness of humanity that
identifies the way forward it's not
about individuals deciding for everyone
else what's going to happen and so I
think what we have to have are profound
and nuanced conversations where we're
discussing this and we can't just seek
all the reasons why we're going to fail
we need to seek the reasons why we're
going to succeed we need to seek and
like within this current crisis that we
see there's some really very interesting
outcomes how many people are sitting
around with their families or just
communicating with their families over
long distances but feeling from their
heart how important it is to have family
and friends and make a connection love
communities and so this is very
different from the rat race you know
running around so one of the things that
I've been feeling lately is like you can
succeed in the rat race but you're still
a rat you know if you do that you know
you might want to relax into trying to
figure out what it means to be a human
being rather than then get on the
treadmill and run around in a circle no
but I completely utterly agree like
right now what's happening here I'm a
yoga just to give you one example like I
moved to Majorca because I'm interested
in the bioregional transformation that
includes the activity that ecosystems
restoration camps would train people up
to do which is large landscape
restoration both to bring back forests
and healthy rivers and also to grow
healthier regenerative agriculture food
and biomaterials all of that if they're
the reason I moved to my Orca is because
Majorca has an island is a great example
of such a bioregional case study and
completely humble
knowing that one person can't change
that system but I wanted to see what by
making a commitment to one place I could
do over 20 30 40 years building Network
and nurturing a vision and a collective
activity and now because of what's
happened
this isn't like what you said 16 million
people got unemployed in the United
States here there's barely a million
people and more than half of them are
now unemployed because there is like 80
percent is tourism industry yeah
there is no tourism anymore and I
completely agree that what I would love
to see for this island is to not for the
government to spend money so people can
just mill around until maybe in 2021 or
2022 they recuperate some form of
business in the tourism industry
pretending they can go back to where
they were I would love to see everybody
engaging in ecosystems restoration and
getting this it--like if he if the
government has to pay people a basic
citizen income and and money anyway we
might as well engage people with the
land again and yes this kind of work so
I'm so with you I'm just saying how do
we fit it into these realities of of a
bio region like my yokomo I think you
you have to have a we have to we have to
reach calm we have to be all of us need
to become calm and to you know the
answers don't come intellectually
exactly they come from being able to
understand it and imagine it and then
they come from sharing having a shared
intention yeah I think so in order for
people to grasp this there's a great
deal of uncertainty there's a great deal
of anxiety now so it's very important to
be calm in this situation it's very
important to be empathetic
and compassionate now so seeking the
intellectual reasons I mean I can tell
you my opinion I can tell you what I
think but I don't think that's going to
be the determining factor for what
happens I think that that might help to
inform what happens and so I'm I think
we are we have both a crisis we have a
crisis and it's both serious risk and
it's great opportunity now so the
opportunity seems to be in the economic
realm which you started to discuss I
think on the one hand we can offer this
ecosystem restoration camps methodology
as a way to put in central kitchens and
to have zero waste zero packaging zero
pollution only organic only biodynamic
only local only Fairtrade food and we
can feed people this way now that's one
major benefit in a crisis like this so
instead of having kind of sad tragic
soup kitchens
let's have joyous meals together in a
slow food movement that's not wasting
food that's taking this food out of the
transactional economic system and making
it available to everybody so there's
going to be no waste there's going to be
no packaging no pollution and there's
going to be no hunger because we're
going to commit that the community eats
everybody in this community eats now
that's first second if we're able to
generate simple safe comfortable warm
semi-nomadic housing options like
teepees or yours or Bedouin tents or
Safari tents that are acceptable for
people
live in those people who are homeless
for instance would love this but I've
been on Safari have you been on safari
in Africa
it's lovely so it's a nice way to live
I've been in yurts in Mongolia and
teepees in the plains they're elegant
architectural II culturally brilliant so
they're nice to stay there so having a
safety in that we know that like there's
going to be we can take care of
homelessness we can take care of hunger
next we need to take care of employment
so most of the employment in the
existing economy is just to buy and sell
junk or worse it's speculation between
the cost price and interest-bearing debt
which is essentially just this kind of
corrupt non economy it's a type of
indentured servitude
so that's bigger than the real economy
of extraction manufacturing and buying
and selling and then you have all this
and all this other stuff so so that
economy is failing and we need to
recognize this that economy actually has
failed long ago because it's devastated
vast areas of the planet it's created
billions of desperately poor people and
super rich them so you know it's it's a
failure so what are we going to do now I
I don't think we need to attack the
existing economy are the existing powers
they need to take care of themselves and
like you said if they're able to right
the ship and don't sink it now that's
good that's good definitely that'll be
more time to prepare but if they're
unable to right the ship then the ship's
going down now so what are we going to
do
ecosystem restoration camps with central
kitchens and the ability to take care of
people at this time would be critical
are is critical and if we can apply this
to the refugees and the migrants and the
homeless and the post traumatic stress
disorder veterans even better so
the ideas which are within this are so
important for the current situation and
important for the restoration of the
ecological systems for future
generations so there are many reasons
why this should happen but how do you do
that is not up to an individual to say
well we're going to do it this way so
John said we're gonna all go that's not
the way it works the people who are
leading are the organizations for
instance via organic in Mexico or the
the the group in India or the group in
Somalia or the or the second community
in Egypt and of course Finn Dorn Tamara
and Ann are oval and Occidental Arts and
ecology here in California all of these
have been working for decades and now
we're we're seeing that we have to bring
all this together into a mycelial
Network where everything that's learned
immediately goes around the world so if
we learn how to grow fungal inoculants
that can massively increase fungal
availability in soils then we need to
teach everybody how to do that right
away and when we have these things in
place and we're all dedicated to this
and we're also we also have to do
something else besides these I would say
necessary things that we have to do we
also have to slow down stop consuming so
much have no pollution and we need to
have an interaction and where can we do
that we can do that in ecosystem
restoration camps and when people go
through ecosystem restoration camps they
can all find out do I agree with this do
I want to work with each other for the
the well-being of everyone that's where
you get the the change now I completely
as I hear your vision and just see
understand like i i've been i dropped
out or dropped in or whatever you want
to call it in in 1999 i moved to
southern spain wanting to set up an
environmental education center and
little community if he people about how
to restore the land put strawberry
buildings up compost toilets and organic
gardens permaculture all of that and i
traveled in a VW van around europe
visiting a lot of these sites and i've
slept in years all of that they they I
completely see how all of that is such a
amazing emergency response to the
current crisis and the migrant crisis
and there's huge potential for that
there's also somehow this linking into
how do we because we don't know exactly
how quickly the dying system is gonna
die and the midwifing is gonna happen
for the new system we wanted to birth
and so I feel that linking these
initiatives with local government and in
absolute commitment is just an it's just
a wider more scale linked approach where
we this is a participatory project
anyone who chooses to act and lead is
the leader so you know all you have to
do is say oh I'm I am part of the
ecosystem restoration camps movement I
want it to go in this direction I want
to go to the mayor or I want to go to
the governor or I want to go to the
president and I want to say look we can
do this please do everyone has that
opportunity no one is is is says well
don't do that or ask me what's going on
this is happening around the world now
so there are already camps in six
different continents and as this emerges
then they all have to make their way as
though junk we had a conversation I
think it was actually inside the
universal hall into
was at 14 when you were basically going
pregnant with this vision and I think
that was as nothing since I mean wow I'm
really amazing to see how sounding that
note has just sort of moved into a
vacuum of people wanting to say I I
don't I want to stop talking about
regeneration I want to do it and I want
to do it with the land I love here and
that's I and I mean I'm like I don't
know if you if you saw this I send it to
you a few weeks back a PDF of a friend
of mine who here on Majorca and has
started what it's called Bali Aerosmith
and the idea is to basically start with
every little pocket of land that a
private land owners willing to turn over
to be turned into an agroforestry system
and just here as we go along
and in that process plant at least a
million trees but not as just any type
of trees but as agroforestry edible
forest food and and and biomaterials
production systems and and em but I also
think by bringing in common land and
that's why I've been I love the way that
there is a sort of link in terms of
genesis between common land and ERC's
because well common land speaks more to
conventional land owners larger land
owners associations of of
agriculturalists that might even
currently be more conventional I see
that that's the pattern that I faced
here in Majorca and so for me that's a
really interesting strategy to to
actually present to the locals this
possibility of partnering with common
land through existing associations of
land owners and then partnering with a
few pockets to create little ecosystem
restoration camps and I think this
perfectly serves this perfectly serves
the movement so I would absolutely agree
to this but this is not about so I'm
able to decide what I do
so you know I see the way forward as
ecosystem restoration camps because it
empowers the maximum number of people to
participate and that has the biggest
impact and that I understand from my
experiences and my observations that
everyone is equal so there are no there
is no real hierarchy because we're all
going to die
maybe the co vid 19 is telling us this
to that that we're all equal and what
we've done in the past is we've changed
the world into this materialistic world
where you pay for your rights and if you
don't have any money to pay for your
rights you don't have any rights this is
not the way forward this is a recipe for
tremendous suffering world war
revolution it's going to be bad so we
need to figure out how do you give back
the sovereignty and the dignity and the
creativity and the the the energy the
the results so now we have a we talk
about workers so workers are sitting on
their sofa watching TV if they're not
working and art what are they working at
or how many people love what they're
doing and are working at something that
they are their hearts and entire being
is is satisfied by what they're doing
many people are just trying to get a
paycheck to survive and so what are they
doing sometimes they're making plastic
googas sometimes they're doing nothing
you know that's that's of great
importance just to get this money what
we need is for everyone's work to be
meaningful to do something that has
something to do with life that has
something to do where they're satisfied
the intellectually spiritually satisfied
that they're doing what's right
this has not yet emerged we need to to
realize this so this is another way when
I see the ecosystem restoration camps as
being is is this place to experiment and
if you're using if you're using for
instance common land or other other
methodologies that's great but the
choice is common land so common land
must say oh we love ecosystem
restoration camps and that's what we're
going to support here and at the other
side we're going to continue to do what
we've been doing so right now the large
scale things which are invested are
threatened by by the collapse of the
system so now you need the ecosystem
restoration camps even more and we need
to find the alternatives I would
recommend for instance that real
question is what is money now we think
that the money is coming to us from
these capital formations which have been
developed over historical time and we
can talk about that if you want to but
the fact of the matter is that there is
another type of value that has been zero
in the existing economy well that can't
be right
that's disenfranchised billions of
people and made them desperately poor at
the edges of deserts so so how do we how
do we address these how do we connect
those two issues how do we say oh look
they're reforesting they're restoring
the grasslands they're restoring the
wetlands like that's real value so
that's got to be the basis of wealth
that's got to be the basis of the
economy so if that's the economy then
you can give people an income for doing
this and if you want to go back to the
other way and you want to say okay we
have to use business as usual because we
have the governments and we have these
capital formations and these are the
workers that you know you have to have
this conversation with everyone not with
me only but with everyone I know what I
feel about it I've been did
like you are preaching the converted
we're on the say no I'm talking to you
and did anybody else who's watching this
recording but but what what what I mean
is but for me the only neurons where I
feel like in terms of energy but what
I'm trying to explore with you
but in not by saying that I'm right or
wrong is this M how to not be a divisive
force between the dying world and the
birth of that being and if it means in
the right moment at the right time not
necessarily saying what is 100 percent
right but to build the bridge to stay to
keep people on board rather than to keep
the frontiers coming up like right now
what I see is M here my yoga lots of
unemployed people that have for decades
only worked in tourism and all they know
is tourism for them to reconnect them to
the love of the island to the beauty of
la Isla de la calma the the calm islands
that this place was and then to
reconnect them to the which is already
happening right now in the crisis the
local farmers are starting that like
I've been for years been eating organic
vegetable boxes from from a local farmer
who I know who comes every Tuesday and
brings me part of that the harvest but M
now everybody is experiencing that again
like people are suddenly hearing news
flashes about the local milk factory is
saying and we don't sell our milk to the
tourists anymore because there aren't
any tourists can we get the mayor keen
to buy our milk again please and the
Maya Tina saying of course well by local
mode instead of imported milk and so
somehow this has turned up the contrast
on doing that great yeah but it's also
the bizarre things like I mean for the
vegans it's hard to hear but here on the
island there were people who were just
growing lambs for Easter for right now
and they would kill the lamb just to
take them straight to their hotels for
the Easter business now there is no
Easter business now there is no
infrastructure to put these lamb
to freeze these lands may I suggest
something parties parties as soon as as
either either distributed parties where
you or it's ridiculous I'm not even
allowed into the street to go for a walk
or do some exercise that's like well
we're literally under house arrest
police controlled with police patrolling
the streets and finding people six
hundred to a thousand euros for
disobeying if they decide that they want
to buy some sweets for their children
and that's intense that's really intense
this is not this is not happening here
we're asked to wear masks and gloves and
you know so we have masks and gloves and
I just right for the first time like it
for me it's been such a teach others
because I haven't thought as much about
a punitive system that thinks it's right
to take people's freedom just because
they've sold a bit of weed and I mean
feeling now right now what it's like to
just be locked in my own house and only
be allowed out for one big shop once a
week and if they catch me any other way
they can find me and think they are
controlling it like I'm stuck in a flat
my my mother's house is empty and it's
only 15 minutes away from here and it
has a bit of garden where I could plant
stuff I'm not legally allowed to move to
that house I would break the law if I
did and there's police between here and
there that would probably off us from
getting there because you can't have
more than one person in the car it's
like suddenly I'm living what it's like
to be in an oppressed regime and and but
I'm also reason realizing how bloody
fortunate I've been that I'd lived into
my forties to have that experience like
how privileged I have been in so many
ways and yeah
and I think that's what this is doing to
so many people in different ways and
that we if we learn also that all the
menial workers that that
in the streets asking for bigger
salaries and now the ones keeping people
alive and keep systems going it's
amazing so I think we I think these are
this is a surprising moment I think it
was described to me I don't know if I
mentioned this to you earlier but this
was described to me as a flux in time
and space or something you know like
there are new dimensions opening up and
you can go through a portal to the other
side or you can fall through a hole you
know so like if we fail to keep our
spirits up fail to survive this you fall
through a hole if you and the millions
millions of people are falling through
the hole now that's the reality and we
have to be aware that this is happening
and also I think on the other side you
have these sort of reactionary I mean
it's almost fascist type responses so
you see this emerging that that there
are people who just want to be in
control but it wasn't I mean I would
wonder what your opinion is on this
because of course this discussion has
been around now that that we're really
at this point either it's full taking
responsibility direct participatory
democracy on the ground people enabled
by subsidiarity where they can make
choices about their place their region
their community in global collaboration
or you get the ai-controlled super state
like in China where people that ratings
on how often they smile in class yeah
and I think you're gonna have to do this
on a distributed horizontal way yeah
don't think you can have like even China
experienced this early on in communism
they tried to determine the
what agricultural systems would be used
or and that's ridiculous the local
people know much more about here their
biodiversity and what's growing in their
region so it's it was it was a miserable
failure so and I think the trend over
historical time has been toward
individual rights now that may have gone
too far with these people who are sort
of nihilistic there's a nihilism aspect
to materialism where they don't nobody
cares about nobody believes in anything
nobody cares about other people and they
just want more stuff well that that's
gotta stop you know that's really the
the extreme expression of the worst
possible stuff but where we are where we
are now is that human civilization is at
risk we talked about this at the at the
Commonwealth Fame and we thought it was
from climate change but so climate
change is an existential risk nuclear
weapons are an existential risk they're
all symptoms of you the no value system
but it's human civilization that's at
risk not the earth or life and so what
we need to do is we need to have a deep
processing of what it means to be human
beings and and that this is our time and
we are called to do certain things so
it's very important to define and
understand what are the things that
we're called to do so we're called to
address the climate issues address the
ethological disruptions that have taken
place over historical time we're called
to treat everyone equally find out find
a way that human civilization can
include everyone and engage everyone and
empower everyone rather than enriching a
few and and disenfranchising billion
if we don't take that step we're in
serious trouble now so we're at the edge
here of them but we also have to stop
the toxicity and not only stop the
toxicity but we have to to clean it all
we have to we have to take these blood
feuds that are connected to thousands of
years ago one brother killed another
brother and lied about it and then now
hundreds of generations later nobody
remembers the original crime but
everybody but this is so fascinating
that it is like because what often
happens because we're both very
passionate about the ecosystems
restoration part but to understand that
regeneration is also where you were just
going is is also deeply social and it is
actually trauma work and grief work and
and and going deep about understanding
connection and the deeper questions who
are we where are we going why are we
here who have we obliged to what is it
to be human and is life a planetary
process or are we just am i fighting for
individual survival it's I mean it the
whole worldview of even feeling trapped
in the skin not understanding that you
are walking ecosystem I'm a walking
ecosystem I'm a talking ecosystems
restoration it starts with drinking some
caffeine and and good clean water and to
get the right microbiome in your in your
gut huh I think I think it's also that
we we need to be considering an
understanding of the evolution of human
consciousness or the evolution of human
knowledge so somehow yeah I was a
journalist so I just ran around taking
pictures and showing people what was
going on but then I started to research
ecology and when I did this
I realized that we all have a very
limited understanding about things and
the further that you go in understanding
the life systems on the earth the sort
of more grounded or more more more aware
you are of how fragile life is so we're
all living for a few decades and that's
it and it happens you know life I would
say death is easy
life is hard so it's hard to live where
you're conscious of what's going on
where your your life's energy is focused
and concentrated and making something
manifest and I think these are the
things that I've been learning about how
do you do that
and you don't do it by yourself we are
meta organisms so when we when we only
think of ourselves we're very limited
but when we stop thinking about
ourselves but we think about sort of
more collaborative and more larger scale
I mean Einstein said if if you can't
solve the problem make it bigger you
know I think that's a very good idea
make it bigger and when you make it
bigger you go well I can't deal with
that personally but then you realize
well there is an agency that can take
care of that it's humanity if the
worldview is that we're all part of this
that we're moving forward that it's in
our interests and the interests of our
children and future generations to work
for the ecological systems and let me
ask a question there because that for me
this is a really interesting point
because I can sometimes also fall a
little bit into the kind of belief where
I said like if we only all kind of had a
full understanding of astronaut Han
interbeing
type like the story of interbeing being
connected if we all were just keen to
live the questions together and create
regenerative cultures as the language I
would be using here and but what I'm
increasingly thinking is that as human
development whether you use like
if you just using that as an example of
the kind of dynamics of how people go
through different stages and go from a
sort of egocentric to a family centric
tribe centric specie centric life
centric goes one moment just how long do
you think we're going to need because I
let's wrap it up in ten minutes okay
sorry it's so nice to hear from people
because I'm still sort of I'm a
houseguest but I'm I'm trapped lovely
family here but yeah just like there was
this key point of basically how do we
need to like rather than assuming that
we somehow manage to get everybody on
board and really actors how do we
actually work with the system where
they'll always be some people who are
still on the journey and who everybody
is on the journey yeah yeah soon
everybody somewhere on the journey and
that journey leads to another dimension
when we leave this dimension and so in
while we're in this to me
and while we're together in this
dimension we need to see that actually
what we what we think what we do what we
say how we act all has an impact and and
I think in terms of what we are what
we're mainly talking about right now we
have a society which is in great
confusion so the it's polarized in
different ways it's it's all over the
place it's a mess we're in the Chinese
parlance we're living in interesting
times which is not a good thing you know
we would rather we would rather look at
the moon and drink warm wine and write
poetry but instead who are dealing with
these these enormous forces which are
changing society and we know we know the
mistakes in the economy we know the the
the mistakes the corruptions in
governance we know the lack of freedom
and which takes away the responsibility
from the from the people which is a big
mistake because the people have the
power and the ability and the majority
of people are good this is I think it's
what I've mainly learned and what I
would say about this that you what you
just said about that that having
everybody we're not going to have
everybody we don't need everybody yet
everybody will do what their ever
they're going to do we need a critical
mass and this critical mass has to see
that okay whether it happens quickly or
it happens gradually or it happens in
fits and starts or however it happens
we're going in another direction we're
going toward an ecologically bio diverse
functional
earth systems and we're going toward a
human civilization so I would I would
actually make sure that there is a
discussion about primacy and about
secondary systems so governance and
economics these are secondary systems
the private and primary system is the
are the oxygenated atmosphere
hydrological cycle the soil fertility
and the biodiversity so we have to know
this and we have to understand that the
gradual trend in human civilization is
toward human rights for dignity toward
freedom toward justice now those things
are threatened by fascism by
totalitarianism
by and by corruption taken by by lies
and by those who wish to control by
violence you know the majority people
they're not interested in violence but
somebody is so somebody is arming vast
numbers of people with huge huge things
but the great thing about being a
journalist was I saw the armies refused
to fire and the collapse of the Soviet
Union and this changes in East Europe
because the armies are the children of
the people so when push comes to shove
they're not gonna do what some horrible
tyrant wants them to do they're gonna
say no that's my mother my father my
grandmother my brother and sister out
there and they're gonna stop that's what
happened after well you know that's what
happened with the collapse of the Soviet
Union that the leaders issued live
ammunition and the the troops and all
kinds of country said no I don't believe
I will and that's an interesting thing
you know if the guy says shoot them you
know how I mean and they go no yeah then
they turn around and say hey hey buddy
you know forget it
you're done now so what look at what
happened there tell chesco I mean child
chess goes like the ultimate example
but even even what happened in the last
four weeks that and ultimately the world
over people were willing to take this
the destructive murderous economic
system that has actually killed more
people than the virus and drive it
against the wall pretty much in order to
save the old and the weak and and and I
think that's it that's a sign that we're
not as horrible a species as sometimes
we're taught in school and we should
we're not a horrible species we're where
human beings were just a flawed you know
we're not perfect
hmm you have choice we have freewill and
we often make the wrong the wrong
decisions you know so so we need to also
be gentle and forgiving and
compassionate and empathetic and realize
that well nobody's perfect but but the
the closer we come to our ideals the the
better we define our values and we act
on our values the better things come out
now I I think that where we are right
now is that the ecosystem restoration
camps is an idea whose time has come
there the need for this is enormous it
is the lowest cost and the highest
outcome in terms of engaging people
protecting people at this high risk
moment and engaging them in what we need
to do to ensure sustainability and
survival of human civilization in the
future
so so then when I would what I would
recommend is all who understand this
they need to come together and if that
reaches critical mass whatever that may
be whatever size you know but anyway
everyone who understand it understands
it is an ally now
and it's not about institution building
it's it's not about personal gain
it's not about one country or another
it's about human civilization wherever
they understand this acting to feed the
people acting to give them temporary
shelter so that no one unnecessarily
suffers at this time and then within
this in this infrastructure that we're
talking about which is the cheapest way
to do this collective eyes the central
kitchens and feed everybody remove the
food from the transactional economics so
that there's no food wasted I mean the
idea that half of the food that's grown
is thrown away or something like that is
ridiculous
feed everybody now and then engage these
people in ecosystem restoration in a
gentle way I would recommend five hours
a day five days a week and the rest of
the time study have slow food beautiful
meals together do recreation slowly come
back together after this crisis is over
and built the future hmm so tell me
before we wrap up maybe if I get this
out before next Saturday and maybe tell
me a little bit of a plan for what well
next Saturday is about Saturday Saturday
is about maybe having this conversation
that we're having but having it be in
public and having it be very calm
so trying we we think it's necessary for
instance the indigenous people in this
region will open the conversation mhm
and there'll be many people talking
about human human restoration societal
restoration not just
ecosystem restoration and we'll talk
about the camps we'll talk about social
and human restoration will talk about
regenerative agriculture in the water
cycle then we'll talk about I saw a
great culture regenerative agriculture
Andy Lankford and Tom Duncan and the
jane goodall I've just been talking with
Jane Goodall I think she's preparing to
participate and also to promote it we're
going to look at also the economics of
Ilham is invited to present the common
land and we'll talk to the people who
are doing the kiss the ground it's a
been a group working to promote
regenerative agriculture mainly and
second yes set him it'll either I think
it's either he'll me or Maximilian
Abhilash one of those two i saw Andy was
there quite a few times Langford from
Valley University and well he's going to
be talking mainly I think we have him in
the in the part talking about Syria he's
been talking with the United Nations and
has a plan to go into Syria and we're
gonna have people from Somalia who are
working and we're going to have the
Indian camp is in Bihar it's actually in
crisis now there's a hundred thousand
people walking from Delhi to Bihar all
the people who were sellers or you know
street sellers or anything they're all
gone you know they have to leave and so
they're they're headed for Bihar and
they're worried about feeding them so I
think I think they're gonna say hey this
is maybe the sharp edge of the spear
here and you know this is where we are
also talking
about how ecosystem restoration camps
movement can help in these kinds of
things and we have to look at this but
people are suffering all over the world
but I mean you're in another level of
suffering if you're walking to Bihar and
you have no food when you get there you
know that I mean what I find is so
important at this point is as you kind
of was addressing earlier is to really
link up all these networks because for
example Ruth Andrade who works with lush
mmm has been really active behind the
scenes with this The Blueprint Network
which grew out of the the Eco village
network but it's basically people who
are permaculture agroforestry those kind
of teachers who have experience of going
into crisis areas and rebuilding after
after disaster and and we I think we
like that's where I feel why I'm so
passionate as an educator about ERC's is
that it's the the mechanism of scaling
up the scaling up or scaling out the
scaling up getting more people engaged
and really that means like I'm super
excited to see education in ecosystems
restoration camps now doing this online
course where they highlight some really
amazing story that my friend Galen with
by matrix water who you met at fin horn
and I think we really need to bring the
movement together and EEOC's is it's a I
I would call it like a living laboratory
that should be available to all the
organizations and all the individuals
who need to use it so all those people
who studied permaculture for decades and
then don't have anything to do you know
have may have a lot of trouble they're
all trying to sell PDC courses or
they're trying to grow vegetables to
sell in the farmer's market or something
they have to they have to inhabit the
ecosystem restoration camps and be the
trainers and they should have jobs for
life there and there's there's another
thing we're talking about we're talking
about value and alternative currency
really and the and the bridge but
Queen the alternative currency and the
existing economic system so what earth
bank is talking about is a debit card
connected with a token the token is a
blockchain protected value system
similar to what you would if you went to
the supermarket and you bought some
groceries and they gave you some stamps
and you said you know you can get some
dishes or something but but basically
the value in this token is determined by
all who trust in in the token so
everybody who uses the token basically
sets the this group who's creating it
and using it gets to set the value so
when when people do more work they can
get more value in their thing
we can even denominator in fiat currency
and put it into the debit card where it
can be used in the in the existing
economy everywhere in the world and by
doing this in all the camps around the
world we've created an alternative
economic system which could be very
helpful for those people who are
refugees or homeless or whatever and
then it's just about a matter of being
in deep meditation and working together
hard to not make this about individual
interest we have to understand that
there's already been two Nobel prizes
for the understanding that if you pursue
individual interests to the point that
it erodes the collective interest it's
not in your interest anymore so it's in
all of our interests to move forward and
and economics and social and
psychological and social psychological
health we are all needed well I mean
it's it's what you know you know it like
I call it that the shift from
competitive advantage to collaborative
advantage it's it's definitely it just
doesn't make sense like and that's
that's the enlightened self-interest is
to understand you need to help everybody
to do well
the best way to do well and so use well
but ya know I'm really looking forward
to it um you can you can let me know how
you see me
is it is it three hours everybody well
if it's up to you so the people the
people who who are who are presenting
something they're you know they're gonna
be called like ten minutes before
they're going to go on to make sure that
they're there but we're gonna have a
green room and that green room will be a
zoom conversation we're not going out on
soon we're going the people who are
presenting are going in you're welcome
to be on the in the green room for three
hours or whatever it may even be more
but you don't you can come or go or
whatever you want again and and then I
believe we're going to record that
conversation and we're gonna have
another if you want to get on the
livestream you might have to go so
you'll be in touch there'll be a
moderator in the in the green room zoom
and if somebody's chosen to go into the
thing they're gonna have to go to
another zoom okay and then they'll then
they'll be switched through the switcher
to the very fast internet connection
going out we're having music it's lovely
the Appalachia rising playing for change
it's gonna be really quite nice we're
coming from a recording studio I'll be
tired because just before it starts I do
it to our online workshops with some
people in Lisbon on education and
regenerative cultures but maybe that
just boost me up so it's been a lovely
to connect with you and I'll see you
next Saturday and we're well on the same
mission and I'm deeply grateful you out
there man my earth is your earth and I
heart is your heart my spirit is your
spirit we are working together as simple
as that
ul okay thanks so much bye-bye right